x marks the spot
i've covered some pretty awesome
barbells but when you consider
functionality tensile strength and price
is the x training competition barbell
one of the best options out there it's a
multi-purpose bar meaning it can handle
your power lifting cross training and
olympic lifting needs it has a tensile
strength rating of a whopping 215 000
psi and a low price tag makes it an
absolute steal
[Music]
what's up everybody you know the deal
it's jake back in the barbing garage gym
for today's review i've got the x
training competition barbell i'm excited
to walk you guys through everything this
barbell has to offer from the price some
features pros and cons and of course who
should or who should not buy this
barbell but before we get started with
any of that
i got to let you know we have reviewed a
lot of barbells on varbin.com and if you
want to browse our best list just search
barbind best barbells and you can find
out for yourself which ones that we like
the best okay so what do i like about
the x training competition barbell so
for starters it has a tensile strength
rating of 215 000 psi
you don't know what that means
essentially it's how much weight and
force that a barbell can handle before
it's going to bend break maybe even
fracture on you so since this is pretty
close to that max threshold which is
around 230 000 psi this barbell is
pretty elite in that category if you're
an olympic lifter or a crossfitter
you're probably gonna love this barbell
does not have a center knurling which is
gonna completely eliminate the chances
of you irritating your chest during
those type of lifts the bronze bushings
in both of the sleeves are going to
allow them to spin like the tilt-a-whirl
at the carnival
and the knurling on this bar is not
going to tear up your hands when you're
doing high rep exercises since this
comes the 20 kilogram and a 15 kilogram
option
is really a bar available for everybody
and plus
with a super low price tag
this bar is a steal especially once you
compare it to the other barbells that
are similar on the market
okay now there are a few potential cons
you might run into with this barbell
starting with the knurling here if
you're a power lifter odds are you're
looking for a barbell that has a deep
cut knurling you're not going to find
this here because it is a multi-purpose
bar and those typically don't have a
very deep cut knurling which that was
really the first thing that popped out
in my eyes
not very abrasive at all my hands tend
to sweat a lot while i'm working out so
if you're like me you may not like this
barbell it's not very abrasive on your
hands now i do personally like that this
barbell does not have a cinder knurling
because it's not going to irritate my
chest if i decide to do some power
cleans
but there are some of you out there that
are going to want that grip maybe so
that it can stick to your chest a little
bit more as well as on your back while
you're doing back squats and if you're
wanting to do some suitcase deadlifts
this probably is not the bar for that
because you know you don't have that
extra grip right there to hang on to
[Music]
okay so let's talk about some money now
this barbell is available at an
extremely impressive price tag of around
230 bucks which is an awesome deal
especially once you consider the quality
that you're getting here
if it had a tensile strength rating of
around 150 000 psi
that might make more sense to me but
this bar is in the upper echelon of
tensile strength plus you get free
shipping so you're telling me you're
going to spend under 300
on this beast of a barbell
dude sign me up
for around 230 bucks you can fully kit
out your home gym with some bumper
plates
a squat rack you name it plus you can
also split up your purchase into four
interest-free payments of around 60
bucks with a firm which really goes to
show even more how much of a deal you're
gonna be getting here
okay so let's talk about the build now
with the x training elite competition
barbell this bar is pretty much of a
stud the alloy steel used to make this
barbell does have a tensile strength
rating of 215 000 psi
it also has a black chrome plating on it
which is going gonna give you some rust
and corrosion resistance plus it looks
pretty sweet too i gotta say the bronze
bushings in the sleeves are gonna allow
them to spin for your olympic and
crossfit training needs but they're not
gonna spin out of control so you can
still focus on your power lifting
movements like a bench press the
knurling here like i said it's not very
abrasive but for some of you out there
who are just now getting into
weightlifting you have a little bit of
some softer hands might be ideal for you
because it's not going to tear them up
while you're working out this bar is
available in 20 and 15 kilogram options
so the 20 kilogram ball we have here 86
inches in length with 16 and a half inch
loading sleeves and a handle diameter of
28 millimeters the 15 kilogram bar
79 inches in length with 12 and a half
inch loading sleeves and a 25 millimeter
bar
now
some companies do offer a 10 kilogram
bar it's not the case with this barbell
right here
all right guys i'm going to talk a
little bit more about the features now
with this barbell so starting with the
knurling i talked about how it's not
very abrasive and that might be ideal
for some of y'all out there because it's
not going to tear up your hands during
high rep exercises but if you are a
power lifter probably not going to be
too crazy about this bar which that's
something you've got to consider when
you're looking to add this to your home
gym i personally like the fact this does
not have a cinder knurling i can still
keep the bar on my back while i'm doing
my squats but some of y'all like that
center knurl and i understand because
you do get a better grip and it can keep
the bar in place a little bit better the
loading sleeves do have a bit of a
groove pattern but they're not cut very
deep so you might want to go snag
yourself a pair of weight collars just
to make sure that your weight plates or
bumper plates do stay in place
especially if you're doing some power
cleans the bronze bushings that are in
both the sleeves are going to allow them
to spin at a controlled rate and they're
also cost effective compared to olympic
bars that use bearings
the black chrome you're going to find on
this barbell i think it looks really
cool but it's also going to provide some
resistance to rust and corrosion
but you're probably going to have to
give it a little bit extra care
especially if you're in a humid
environment
just to make sure it stays in good
condition for a long time which
you might not have to do that as much if
you had a stainless steel bar
[Music]
okay let's take a quick walk around this
barbell now starting with the fact this
is the 20 kilogram version of this bar
it's also available in 15 kilograms but
remember it's not available in 10
kilograms so if you're looking for a
junior sized bar out there this isn't
going to be it for you okay so once
again this is made from alloy steel it's
coated in black zinc from end to end as
you can tell i personally like that it
brings a nice aesthetic in your gym
which is pretty cool in my opinion now
you don't have a center knurling right
here that's because it's a multi-purpose
bar it's pretty common with barbells
such as this one because you are able to
do olympic and crossfit style lifts
now the overall knurling right here it's
okay but it is a little bit passive i
gotta say so
while you can do your power lifts with
this barbell you know if you have you
know really rough hands or maybe they
sweat or you just really want as good of
a grip as possible this doesn't cut very
deep so it might not bring that to you
so you might want to go and get some
lifting chalk maybe some straps or even
some gloves just to help you out now you
do have dual neural markings right here
on this barbell the ones on the inside
those are set by the international power
lifting federation and the ones on the
outside those are set by the
international weightlifting federation
so it's a nice little touch it's going
to help you out in terms of getting
identical hand placement as you go to
get set up for any wide grip lifts you
might be doing all right so let's move
further down the line here
you do have bronze bushings in the
sleeves and that's going to provide a
nice little spin for you but as you can
tell they don't spin out of control so
that's really nice and that's another
reason that makes this a multi-purpose
bar because it's not going to spin on
you or at least too much as you're bench
pressing it's not going to mess with
your lift and if you look up close you
do have a bit of a grooved pattern right
here on these sleeves that's going to be
helpful in terms of keeping your plates
locked into place but they're not cut
super deep so you know for your own
safety and just to make sure they're not
sliding around on you you know
definitely go and get yourself some
weight collars you know they just slide
right on you can snap them in and that's
really going to help you out in terms of
keeping those plates in their original
placement
[Music]
okay so who should purchase the x
training elite competition barbell
everybody
i'm just kidding but this is a really
good option to consider especially if
you're a beginner and you're looking for
a bar it's not too abrasive it's not
going to tear up your hands during those
high rep exercises
the 215 000 tensile strength rating on
this barbell makes it to where a
beginner can grow with it plus you elite
level lifters out there you can put this
thing to the test as well
the bronze bushings
the lack of a center knurling and the
moderate knurling is going to make this
a really good option for those olympic
lifters and crossfitters out there but
remember the knurling is not very
abrasive so you might want to get some
chalk just to make sure you do get that
grippiness that you're looking for
and for a budget price of 230 dollars
really is budget friendly for nearly
everybody out there
[Music]
okay so who should not purchase this
barbell well not power lifters out there
with hands as tough as a two dollar
stake
you're probably not going to be too
happy about the knurling on this barbell
because it's probably not going to be
grippy enough for you and if you're
looking for a bar strictly for power
lifting it probably isn't the barbell
for you while the sleeves do have a bit
of a groove pattern they're not cut that
deep so for somebody who's not wanting
to use weight collars all the time this
might not be the bar for you although i
definitely recommend you always use a
set of weight collars for your own
safety
i know you guys hate to see me leave but
that's all i got for you today on the x
training elite competition barbell
this bar is straight out of my dreams
it's as versatile as a swiss army knife
it has a tensile strength rating that's
right up there with the best of them and
it's available at a budget friendly
price you can throw almost anything at
it in the weight room and it's gonna
pass with flying colors thanks for
watching everybody i hope this video
helped answer some questions that you
might have about this bar and showed
what you can expect if you're looking to
add this to your home gym
stay on the lookout for my next review
but in the meantime head over to
barban.com not just because i said so
but so you can read and learn more about
this barbell as well as any other
products we've reviewed just search
barbin x training elite competition bar
review you can find all the details we
discussed here today now go hit the
weights i'll see you all next time
[Music]